<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE caseml PUBLIC " -//Butterworths//DTD XML CASE REPORTS VER 1.0//EN" "file:////E:/URJ/dtd/caseml.dtd"><caseml><case series="urj" year="2014" bcnum="BC201400004" jur="nsw">
<headnote>
<caseinfo><casename>OWNERS &mdash; STRATA PLAN NO 62022 v SAHADE</casename>
<courtinfo>
<court courtid="nswsc">Supreme Court of New South Wales &mdash; Common Law</court>
<coram><judge>Rothman</judge> J</coram>
<fileno>2013/154156</fileno>
<dates><sitting>10&nbsp;September 2013</sitting><decdate day="30" month="01" year="2014"/></dates>
<mnc year="2014" courtid="nswsc" casenum="3" name="Owners - Strata Plan No 62022 v Sahade"/></courtinfo>
<editor date="13/01/2014 11:42:54&nbsp;PM">velascoe</editor>
</caseinfo>
<catchwordgrp>
<catchwords><key>STATUTORY CONSTRUCTION</key><keysum>Strata Schemes Management Act 2007</keysum><keysum>Validity of meeting</keysum><keysum>Failure to give notice to lot owner</keysum><keysum>Insufficient notice</keysum><keysum>Strict compliance necessary</keysum><keysum>Appeal dismissed.</keysum></catchwords></catchwordgrp>
<held>
<referleg>
<legref jur="nsw" year="2005" type="act" print="yes"> <legname>Civil Procedure Act 2005</legname> </legref>
<legref jur="nsw" year="2007" type="act" print="yes"> <legname>Local Court Act 2007</legname> </legref>
<legref jur="nsw" year="1996" type="act" print="yes"> <legname>Strata Schemes Management Act 1996</legname> </legref></referleg>
<conscases use="cited"><casecit><lit>Brown v Bluestone Property Services Pty&nbsp;Ltd</lit><ucit bcnum="BC201005449" mncit="[2010] NSWSC 869">[2010] NSWSC 869</ucit></casecit><casecit><lit>Dargavel v Cameron</lit><ucit bcnum="BC200205868" mncit="[2002] FCA 1234">[2002] FCA 1234</ucit></casecit><casecit><lit>Northumbrian Ice Cream Co Ltd v Breakaway Vending Pty Ltd</lit><ucit bcnum="BC200609566" mncit="[2006] NSWSC 1216">[2006] NSWSC 1216</ucit></casecit><casecit><lit>Project Blue Sky v Australian Broadcasting Authority</lit><ucit mncit="[1998] HCA 28">[1998] HCA 28</ucit><cit year="1998" yrencl="parens" volume="194" series="clr" pgnumber="355">(1998) 194 CLR 355</cit></casecit><casecit><lit>Project Blue Sky; Victoria v Sutton</lit><ucit mncit="[1998] HCA 56">[1998] HCA 56</ucit><cit year="1998" yrencl="parens" volume="195" series="clr" pgnumber="291">(1998) 195 CLR 291</cit></casecit></conscases>
</held>
</headnote>
<judgmentgrp>
<judgment><coram><judge>Rothman</judge> J.</coram>
<p num="y" pnum="1"><text>The plaintiff, The Owners &mdash; Strata Plan No 62022 (the Owners&rsquo; Corporation) appeals from an order of the Local Court dismissing its claim for unpaid strata levies, interest and expenses pursuant to the Strata Schemes Management Act 1996 (the Act) on 22&nbsp;April 2013. The issue is and was the validity of a general meeting at which these levies were imposed.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="2"><text>The appeal has been described by the plaintiff as lodged under s&nbsp;39 of the Local Court Act 2007 (LC Act) (see plaintiff&rsquo;s outline of submissions), which allows an appeal as of right &ldquo;but only on a question of law&rdquo;. Notwithstanding that description, the summons seeks orders granting leave to appeal, which is relevant only to an appeal under s&nbsp;40 of the LC Act, namely &ldquo;a question of mixed law and fact&rdquo;.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="3"><text>The discriminating feature of ss&nbsp;39 and 40 of the LC Act refers to the ground upon which the appeal is taken, not whether the decision impugned, either wholly or so much as is impugned, is a decision on a question of law alone. The grounds raised in the appeal include at least one ground that is only a question of law and other grounds that are questions of mixed law and fact. Each ground is substantive and raises arguable issues. The grounds have been fully argued. To the extent necessary, leave to appeal is granted.</text></p>
<pgrp>
<title>The proceedings in the Local Court</title>
<p num="y" pnum="4"><text>The plaintiff filed a document in the Local Court entitled &ldquo;Plaintiff&rsquo;s Statement of Facts and Issues&rdquo;. It was in the following terms:</text></p>
<p num="n">
<quote><p num="n"><text>FACTS</text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="1."><p num="n"><text>The Plaintiff is an Owners Corporation constituted pursuant to s.11 of the Strata Schemes Management Act 1996 (&ldquo;SSMA&rdquo;).</text></p></li>
<li label="2."><p num="n"><text>The Defendant is the registered owner of lot 3 in Strata Plan 62022.</text></p></li>
<li label="3."><p num="n"><text>On 17&nbsp;January 2012, a Notice of an Annual General Meeting was sent to all owners of lots in Strata Plan 62022 by the Plaintiff including to the Defendant&rsquo;s address recorded in the Plaintiff&rsquo;s strata roll being 755 New South Head Road, Rose Bay NSW 2029.</text></p></li>
<li label="4."><p num="n"><text>At the Annual General Meeting of the Plaintiff on 30&nbsp;January 2012, the Plaintiff raised contributions in accordance with the SSMA as follows:</text></p><p num="n">
<table frame="none" colsep="0">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="col1">Date contribution due</entry>
<entry colname="col2">Date of meeting where contribution raised</entry>
<entry colname="col3">Amount of contribution</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1">1&nbsp;March 2012</entry>
<entry colname="col2">30&nbsp;January 2012</entry>
<entry colname="col3">$3,569.75</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1">1&nbsp;March 2012</entry>
<entry colname="col2">30&nbsp;January 2012</entry>
<entry colname="col3">$16,000.00 (&ldquo;Special Levy&rdquo;)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col1">TOTAL</entry>
<entry colname="col2"></entry>
<entry colname="col3">$19,569.75</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</p></li>
<li label="5."><p num="n"><text>The Defendant was served with a Notice of Levies Due in March 2012, identifying contributions payable of $19,569.75 and as approved at the Annual General Meeting of the Plaintiff on 30&nbsp;January 2012. This notice was served on the Defendant at her address recorded in the Plaintiff&rsquo;s strata roll being 755 New South Head Road, Rose Bay NSW 2029.</text></p></li>
<li label="6."><p num="n"><text>After the commencement of the proceedings, on 3&nbsp;September 2012 the Defendant paid the Plaintiff the sum of $3,569.75, but the Special Levy for $16,000.00, the subject of this claim, still remains outstanding.</text></p></li>
<li label="7."><p num="n"><text>The plaintiff has charged, and continues to charge, the Defendant interest on outstanding contributions the subject of this claim, pursuant to s.79 of the SSMA.</text></p></li>
<li label="8."><p num="n"><text>The plaintiff has charged, and continues to charge, the Defendant expenses it has incurred in recovering the outstanding contributions the subject of this claim, pursuant to s.80 of the SSMA.</text></p></li>
</list>
<p num="n"><text>Issues</text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="9."><p num="n"><text>Whether the Plaintiff has served the Defendant with a Notice of an Annual General Meeting 7 days before the Meeting in accordance with clause 32 of Schedule 2 of the SSMA.</text></p></li>
<li label="10."><p num="n"><text>Whether the Defendant is liable to pay the Plaintiff the following:</text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(a)"><p num="n"><text>$16,000 being the Special Levy.</text></p></li>
<li label="(b)"><p num="n"><text>Interest pursuant to s.79 of the SSMA on the sum of $3,569.75 to 3&nbsp;September 2012.</text></p></li>
<li label="(c)"><p num="n"><text>Interest pursuant to s.79 of the SSMA on the sum of $16,000 to 22&nbsp;April 2013.</text></p></li>
<li label="(d)"><p num="n"><text>The costs of the Plaintiff pursuant to s.80 of the SSMA.</text></p></li>
</list>
</li>
</list>
</quote>
</p>
<p num="y" pnum="5"><text>The defendant took no issue below with the facts alleged or the statement of issues. As a consequence, the defendant accepted (or did not dispute) that on 17&nbsp;January 2012, notice of the Annual General Meeting (AGM) &ldquo;was sent to all owners of lots &hellip; including to the Defendant&rsquo;s address&rdquo;.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="6"><text>The notice, which is in evidence (and was in evidence below) gave notice of a general meeting on 30&nbsp;January 2012. No issue is taken on appeal with the contents of the notice.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="7"><text>The learned magistrate determined that the plaintiff could not establish that it had provided 7 days&rsquo; notice of the relevant general meeting and, as a consequence, dismissed its claim.</text></p>
</pgrp>
<pgrp>
<title>Issues on appeal</title>
<p num="y" pnum="8"><text>The issues agitated by the parties on appeal are (or seek to be) wider than those argued below.</text></p>
</pgrp>
<pgrp>
<title>Service by post</title>
<p num="y" pnum="9"><text>First, the defendant seeks, on appeal, it seems for the first time, to agitate whether the plaintiff has proved that notice was sent.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="10"><text>The defendant correctly submits that, in order to prove that a notice was sent, a party (in this case the plaintiff) has to satisfy the tribunal of fact of certain primary facts: the contents of the document; the placing of the document in an envelope; the addressing of the envelope with the relevant address; the affixing of a stamp (or other tracking/prepaid process); and the physical deposit of the envelope, addressed and stamped, in or at a proper place for postage to be effected (post box or post office): <casecit><lit>Brown v Bluestone Property Services Pty&nbsp;Ltd</lit><ucit bcnum="BC201005449" mncit="[2010] NSWSC 869">[2010] NSWSC 869</ucit></casecit> at&nbsp;[12] per Barrett&nbsp;J; <casecit><lit>Northumbrian Ice Cream Co Ltd v Breakaway Vending Pty Ltd</lit><ucit bcnum="BC200609566" mncit="[2006] NSWSC 1216">[2006] NSWSC 1216</ucit></casecit> at&nbsp;[12] per Brereton&nbsp;J.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="11"><text>The foregoing sets out the primary facts that are necessary to prove in order to establish that a document &ldquo;was sent&rdquo; or &ldquo;was served by post&rdquo;. Here, however, the plaintiff asserted a conclusion of fact, namely, that the notice of the AGM &ldquo;was sent&rdquo; to the defendant&rsquo;s address, from which assertion or pleading the defendant did not dissent.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="12"><text>There was, on the pleadings before the Local Court, an admission of material facts, being that the notice was sent to the defendant&rsquo;s address on 17&nbsp;January 2012. In those circumstances, it was unnecessary, and contrary to the provisions of ss&nbsp;56, 57 and 58 of the Civil Procedure Act 2005, for the plaintiff to seek to prove that which was not a &ldquo;real issue between the parties&rdquo; on the pleadings.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="13"><text>In so far as the learned magistrate required proof of facts that were agreed, the magistrate was in error.</text></p>
</pgrp>
<pgrp>
<title>Requisite notice</title>
<p num="y" pnum="14"><text>Nevertheless, a &ldquo;real issue&rdquo; between the parties was whether, on the agreed facts, namely, that notice was sent by post on 17&nbsp;January 2012 for a meeting called for 30&nbsp;January 2012, sufficient notice was provided for the general meeting.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="15"><text>This second aspect requires the recitation of some preliminary matters. The provisions of cl&nbsp;32(1) of Sch&nbsp;2 of the Act is in the following terms:</text></p>
<p num="n">
<quote><p num="n"><text><emphasis face="bold">32 Persons to whom notice of general meeting must be given</emphasis></text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(1)"><p num="n"><text>Notice of a general meeting of an owners corporation must, at least 7 days before the meeting, be served on each owner.</text></p></li>
</list>
</quote>
</p>
<p num="y" pnum="16"><text>In the foregoing, it is relevant to note the use of the words &ldquo;must&rdquo; and &ldquo;at least&rdquo;. The manifest purpose of the provision, which applies in the circumstances in dispute here, is to compel an owners&rsquo; corporation (or those managing it) to give sufficient notice to those with the requisite interest to attend and participate in such general meetings.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="17"><text>The aforesaid purpose accords with the purpose adopted by the common law in requiring strict adherence to notice provisions for general meetings. In so doing, it distinguished between general meetings and regularly held executive meetings, a summary of which is given by Golderg&nbsp;J in <casecit><lit>Dargavel v Cameron</lit><ucit bcnum="BC200205868" mncit="[2002] FCA 1234">[2002] FCA 1234</ucit></casecit>, in which his Honour, in relation to an industrial organisation, said:</text></p>
<p num="n">
<quote>
<list type="expl">
<li label="[77]"><p num="n"><text>Notwithstanding that the meeting was not a &ldquo;Special&rdquo; meeting, the question still arises whether notice should have been given prior to the meeting of any proposed resolution to appoint Mr&nbsp;Dargavel as State Secretary. The respondents submitted that the meeting was not able to transact business of which notice had not been given and that the resolution appointing Mr&nbsp;Dargavel was therefore invalid and of no effect. Mr&nbsp;Dargavel submitted that the authorities drew a distinction between prior notice of business to be transacted at general meetings of members of organisations and meetings of executive bodies of organisations. He submitted that in the case of special general meetings of members prior notice of business to be transacted was required whereas such prior notice was not required in the case of special meetings of executive bodies. It was submitted that the distinction was based upon the principle that the function of informative notice is to allow a decision to be made by a member as to whether or not the member ought to attend a meeting where the member is not required to attend the meeting. It was said that in the case of a member of an executive body such as a committee of management, each member is under an obligation to attend, not to protect their own interests (which is the reason why members attend) but to make decisions for the good government of an organisation. Mr&nbsp;Dargavel relied upon <casecit><lit>Campbell v Crawford</lit><cit year="1986" yrencl="parens" volume="12" series="fcr" pgnumber="317">(1986) 12 FCR 317</cit></casecit> at 340&ndash;341; <casecit><lit>Johnson v Beitseen</lit><cit year="1991" yrencl="parens" volume="41" series="ir" pgnumber="395">(1991) 41 IR 395</cit></casecit> at 416&ndash;417 and <casecit><lit>Cummings v Macks</lit><ucit bcnum="BC200000133" mncit="[2000] FCA 55">[2000] FCA 55</ucit><cit year="2000" yrencl="parens" volume="96" series="fcr" pgnumber="345">(2000) 96 FCR 345</cit></casecit>.</text></p></li>
<li label="[78]"><p num="n"><text>The meeting of State Council was convened for the purpose of dealing with any business that could not be dealt with at the meeting which had been scheduled for 14&nbsp;August 2002. The agenda attached to the request for the meeting did not refer to the filling of the vacancy in the office of the Victorian State Secretary as that situation had not then arisen. In any event that agenda did not accompany the notice of meeting sent to members of the State Council. At the meeting of State Council the meeting resolved to adopt the agenda set out in [18] above. The resolution to appoint Mr&nbsp;Dargavel only arose as a result of the acceptance by the State Council of Mr&nbsp;Johnston&rsquo;s resignation when correspondence was dealt with. Not all the members of State Council were present at the meeting, there being three apologies.</text></p></li>
<li label="[79]"><p num="n"><text>As a matter of principle, notice of the business to be transacted or considered at a meeting of members of an organisation or of a body of the organisation, whatever be the organisation and whatever by the body forming part of the organisation, should be given to the persons entitled to attend the meeting: see generally Magner, Joske&rsquo;s Law and Procedure at Meetings in Australia 8th ed&nbsp;1994 Ch&nbsp;3. The purpose of such notice is two-fold. First, it is to give those entitled to attend but who are not obliged to attend, the opportunity to decide whether they want to attend. Secondly, it is to give those entitled to attend, whether or not they are obliged to attend by virtue of a position or office which they occupy, an opportunity to consider their attitude to the matters proposed to be discussed at the meeting and whether they wish to prepare for the discussion.</text></p></li>
<li label="[80]"><p num="n"><text>Of course if all the members of an organisation, or body within it, are present at a meeting of the organisation or body, any business may be transacted within the power of such a meeting even where no notice has been given of that business, if all the persons present consent to that business being brought forward.</text></p></li>
<li label="[81]"><p num="n"><text>There have been a number of cases in which resolutions passed at meetings have been held to be invalid because inadequate notice of the business to be transacted or discussed was given to those persons entitled to attend the meeting. Some of those cases involved meetings of members of industrial organisations which were special meetings or meetings called for a particular purpose: <casecit><lit>Campbell v Higgins</lit><cit year="1957" yrencl="parens" volume="3" series="flr" pgnumber="317">(1957) 3 FLR 317</cit></casecit><casecit><lit>McLure v Mitchell</lit><cit year="1974" yrencl="parens" volume="24" series="flr" pgnumber="115">(1974) 24 FLR 115</cit></casecit>, per Joske&nbsp;J at 139&ndash;140.</text></p></li>
<li label="[82]"><p num="n"><text>Notwithstanding these decisions, the caselaw generally draws a distinction between meetings of persons who are not required to attend meetings and meetings of persons who are required to attend by virtue of the position which they occupy. This distinction was recognised by Wilcox&nbsp;J in <casecit><lit>Campbell v Crawford</lit></casecit> (above). A meeting had been called of the Federal Council of the Plumbers and Gasfitters Employees&rsquo; Union of Australia in respect of which an agenda was circulated. A resolution was passed at the meeting to abolish the Geelong Branch of the Union. No notice of this resolution had been given to members of the Federal Council prior to the meeting. Wilcox&nbsp;J held that notice of the proposed resolution did not have to be given to members of the Federal Council prior to the meeting. Wilcox&nbsp;J said at 340:</text></p><p num="n">
<quote><p num="n"><text>There is authority for the proposition that a notice summoning a meeting of members of a branch, in order to be valid, must sufficiently indicate the business intended to be transacted: see <casecit><lit>Campbell v Higgins</lit><cit year="1957" yrencl="parens" volume="3" series="flr" pgnumber="317">(1957) 3 FLR 317</cit></casecit> at 327; <casecit><lit>Winter v McAdam</lit><cit year="1957" yrencl="parens" volume="1" series="flr" pgnumber="210">(1957) 1 FLR 210</cit></casecit> at 211; <casecit><lit>McLure v Mitchell</lit><cit year="1974" yrencl="parens" volume="24" series="flr" pgnumber="115">(1974) 24 FLR 115</cit></casecit> at 134. But these cases are distinguishable from the present. As Evatt&nbsp;J pointed out in <casecit><lit>Cook v Crawford</lit><cit year="1981" yrencl="parens" volume="52" series="flr">(1981) 52 FLR</cit></casecit> at 36, the reason for the rule is &ldquo;to enable any member receiving it to determine in his own interest whether or not he ought attend the meeting&rdquo;. This reason has little application to a meeting of a committee whose members are under an obligation to attend a summoned meeting, not to protect their own interests but to make decisions for the good government of the union.</text></p>
</quote>
</p></li>
<li label="[83]"><p num="n"><text>A similar approach was taken by Gray&nbsp;J in <casecit><lit>Johnson v Beitseen</lit></casecit> (supra). Gray&nbsp;J said at 417:</text></p><p num="n">
<quote><p num="n"><text>Where a rule such as branch r&nbsp;11 [which provided for the calling of Branch Management Committee meetings] makes provision for a meeting of a defined body such as the committee of management, it is ordinarily the duty of each member of that body to attend if notified of a meeting, or if a regular meeting specified in the rules is to be held. No specific notice of the business to be discussed at any such meeting is required. A member of the committee of management remains absent from a meeting at his or her peril.</text></p>
</quote>
</p></li>
<li label="[84]"><p num="n"><text>In <casecit><lit>Cummings v Macks</lit></casecit> (above) Drummond&nbsp;J (with whom Sundberg&nbsp;J agreed), in considering whether s&nbsp;181 of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth) required notice of a motion to remove a trustee at a creditors&rsquo; meeting, recognised the distinction between notices convening meetings of members who were not obliged to attend the meeting and notices convening meetings of members of bodies who were duty-bound to attend the meeting: see 347&ndash;348. Drummond&nbsp;J cited <casecit><lit>Campbell v Crawford</lit></casecit> (supra) with approval, noting that the rule that members of the governing council of a municipal corporation were entitled to an opportunity to consider whether they would attend such meetings because they were duty-bound to attend all of them had been applied to the governing bodies of other organisations such as trade unions.</text></p></li>
</list>
</quote>
</p>
<p num="y" pnum="18"><text>Further the aforesaid purpose and policy is not qualified by a mere exercise in arithmetic. The fact that, in these circumstances, a vote at the meeting by the defendant, if she were to have attended, would not have affected the adoption of the resolution does not affect the validity, or otherwise, of the resolution. The principles underpinning the common law approach include the concept that a person participating in the meeting may be able to persuade others.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="19"><text>Whether the requirement for notice in the Schedule requires strict adherence is ultimately a matter of statutory construction, the modern principles for which were clarified in <casecit><lit>Project Blue Sky v Australian Broadcasting Authority</lit><ucit mncit="[1998] HCA 28">[1998] HCA 28</ucit><cit year="1998" yrencl="parens" volume="194" series="clr" pgnumber="355">(1998) 194 CLR 355</cit></casecit> to make clear that a grammatical or literal meaning may not necessarily be the meaning the legislature is taken to have intended. Rather, the words must be read in context and the provisions of a statute (or other instrument) construed bearing in mind that its provisions were intended to effect harmonious goals.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="20"><text>The defendant urges a more &ldquo;literal approach&rdquo; and emphasises those words already noted above, namely, &ldquo;must&rdquo; and &ldquo;at least&rdquo;. The plaintiff urges a &ldquo;less rigid&rdquo; approach and refers to ss&nbsp;153 and 154 of the Act to evidence an intent to allow practical flexibility and a legislative intent that a breach of the strictures in cl&nbsp;32 would not, of itself, render invalid all resolutions at the meeting.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="21"><text>It is appropriate to recite the relevant parts of ss&nbsp;153 and 154 of the Act:</text></p>
<p num="n">
<quote><p num="n"><text><emphasis face="bold">153 Order invalidating resolution of owners corporation</emphasis></text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(1)"><p num="n"><text>An Adjudicator may make an order invalidating any resolution of, or election held by, the persons present at a meeting of an owners corporation if the Adjudicator considers that the provisions of this Act have not been complied with in relation to the meeting.</text></p></li>
<li label="(2)"><p num="n"><text>An Adjudicator may refuse to make an order under this section but only if the Adjudicator considers:</text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(a)"><p num="n"><text>that the failure to comply with the provisions of this Act did not adversely affect any person, and</text></p></li>
<li label="(b)"><p num="n"><text>that compliance with the provisions of this Act would not have resulted in a failure to pass the resolution or have affected the result of the election.</text></p></li>
</list>
<p num="n"><text>&hellip;</text></p></li>
</list>
<p num="n"><text><emphasis face="bold">154 Order where voting rights denied or due notice of item of business not given</emphasis></text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(1)"><p num="n"><text>An Adjudicator may order that a resolution passed at a general meeting of an owners corporation be treated as a nullity on and from the date of the order if satisfied that the resolution would not have been passed but for the fact that the applicant for the order:</text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(a)"><p num="n"><text>was improperly denied a vote on the motion for the resolution, or</text></p></li>
<li label="(b)"><p num="n"><text>was not given due notice of the item of business in relation to which the resolution was passed&hellip;</text></p></li>
</list>
</li>
</list>
</quote>
</p>
<p num="y" pnum="22"><text>Conduct in breach of a prescribed norm of conduct or process does not necessarily render the result of the conduct void or a nullity: <casecit><lit>Project Blue Sky; Victoria v Sutton</lit><ucit mncit="[1998] HCA 56">[1998] HCA 56</ucit><cit year="1998" yrencl="parens" volume="195" series="clr" pgnumber="291">(1998) 195 CLR 291</cit></casecit> at&nbsp;[36]&ndash;[38]. The effect will be determined by a proper construction of the Act.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="23"><text>It is convenient, at this juncture, to discuss the operation of ss&nbsp;153 and 154 of the Act. First, I deal with s&nbsp;154 of the Act.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="24"><text>In my view, s&nbsp;154 of the Act does not take the plaintiff&rsquo;s submissions as to the construction of cl&nbsp;32 very far, if anywhere. It would be a strained reading of s&nbsp;154(1) of the Act to apply it to a person who was not given notice of the meeting, or given inadequate notice, and, for that reason did not attend. Such a person, on the broadest view, may have been &ldquo;improperly denied a vote&rdquo;, but the expression more aptly describes a person, entitled to vote, who attends a meeting and is denied a vote.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="25"><text>Similarly, a person &ldquo;not given due notice of an item of business&rdquo; does not readily describe the far more extreme position of a person who is not given notice of the meeting at all and is not in attendance. Rather the terms of s&nbsp;154 of the Act provide a &ldquo;ballot inquiry&rdquo; mechanism for the adjudicator to invalidate a resolution passed at a valid meeting because the note on the resolution is affected by irregularity.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="26"><text>Turning to the provisions of s&nbsp;153 of the Act, again, in my view, they do not advance the plaintiff&rsquo;s construction of cl&nbsp;32. It is fair to remark that, unlike s&nbsp;154 of the Act, s&nbsp;153 does not presume (or operate only in circumstances of) an otherwise valid resolution. This is clear from the use of the words &ldquo;persons present at a meeting&rdquo; in s&nbsp;153, as distinct from the use of the phrase &ldquo;resolution passed at a general meeting&rdquo; in s&nbsp;154. Yet each of ss&nbsp;153 and 154 of the Act assume a valid (and properly convened) meeting.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="27"><text>The terms of s&nbsp;153 of the Act apply to irregularities going significantly beyond the requirements of the calling of the meeting. It would apply to a breach of standing orders or the rules of the conduct of the meeting itself: see cll&nbsp;7&ndash;20 of Sch&nbsp;2.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="28"><text>Moreover, it is difficult, if not impossible, to imagine a circumstance where a person was provided no or inadequate notice of the meeting, yet it could be said that the failure &ldquo;did not adversely affect&rdquo; that person, except in circumstances where the person attended the meeting notwithstanding and waived the notice provision. I note, at this juncture, that paras&nbsp;(a) and (b) of s&nbsp;153(2) of the Act must each be satisfied in order for an adjudicator to refuse to make an order invalidating the resolution or the election. Thus, the legislative presumption, with a limited exception, is that non-compliance with any provisions of the Act dealing with the conduct of a meeting will result in an order invalidating any resolution or election held.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="29"><text>In my view the operation of neither ss&nbsp;153 or 154 of the Act qualifies the ordinary and grammatical meaning of cl&nbsp;32 of the Schedule. Nor does either disclose goals or purposes inconsistent with the ordinary and grammatical construction of cl&nbsp;32. Moreover, if the requirement of the Schedule were not, in the intention of the legislature, to be construed strictly, there would be no need for cl&nbsp;27(2) of the Schedule, dealing with ordinary general meetings.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="30"><text>In my view, cl&nbsp;32 requires strict compliance as is evidenced by the use of the word &ldquo;must&rdquo; which is consistent with the use of the words &ldquo;at least&rdquo;.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="31"><text>Once it is held that compliance with cl&nbsp;32 is essential, a number of issues become uncontentious. Firstly, the Interpretation Act 1987 operates to render service to have occurred &ldquo;on the fourth working day after the letter was posted&rdquo;. The evidence established that the notice was posted on 17&nbsp;January 2012 (a Tuesday) and, therefore, in the absence of sufficient evidence to the contrary that raises doubt, it has been effected on 23&nbsp;January 2012 (the next Monday): s&nbsp;76 of the Interpretation Act.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="32"><text>Further, at least 7 days&rsquo; notice must be provided. Pursuant to s&nbsp;36 of the Interpretation Act, the day that the notice was received or effected is excluded from the calculation and, therefore, the first day of the notice period is 24&nbsp;January 2012 and the first day upon which the AGM could be held (and comply with cl&nbsp;32) was 31&nbsp;January 2012. The meeting was held one day too early to comply with the Act.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="33"><text>Lastly, it is necessary to deal with the plaintiff&rsquo;s submissions that the learned magistrate reversed the onus of proof. There are three answers to this submission.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="34"><text>First, if the defendant in asserting the invalidity of the resolution imposing the levy bore the onus, she has satisfied that onus. The uncontroverted evidence was that notice was sent on 17&nbsp;January 2012. Thereafter, the operation of the law, as described above, establishes the insufficiency of notice and the invalidity of the resolution imposing the levy.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="35"><text>Secondly, I do not accept that the defendant bore the onus below. The plaintiff sued on a levy notice. It was required to prove that the levy notice was validly served and related to a valid levy. It proved neither. The issue of whether the levy is valid is answered in the same way as the answer to the question whether the AGM (and resolution) was effective. Further, there was no evidence adduced as to the service of a written notice of the contribution payable, in circumstances where the question of service of the levy notice was not agreed.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="36"><text>Thirdly, [9] of the Statement of Facts and Issues, recited above, makes clear that the validity of the meeting (and the notice thereof) was the issue before the Local Court that would determine liability and the plaintiff ought be bound by the conduct of its case below.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="37"><text>It is unnecessary to deal with any other issue, except to say that nothing in the judgment of the learned magistrate (or, for that matter, in these reasons) depended (or depends) on the actual receipt of the notice. Receipt of the notice is not essential; it is presumed. Service of the notice is essential.</text></p>
<p num="y" pnum="38"><text>The court makes the following orders:</text></p>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(1)"><p num="n"><text>To the extent necessary, leave to appeal granted;</text></p></li>
<li label="(2)"><p num="n"><text>Appeal dismissed;</text></p></li>
<li label="(3)"><p num="n"><text>The plaintiff shall pay the defendant&rsquo;s costs of and incidental to these proceedings, as agreed or assessed. Such costs shall be paid from contributions levied on all lots other than the defendant&rsquo;s lot.</text></p></li>
<li label="(4)"><p num="n"><text>Otherwise, proceedings dismissed.</text></p></li>
</list>
</pgrp>
</judgment>
<caseorder>
<list type="expl">
<li label="(1)"><p num="n"><text>To the extent necessary, leave to appeal granted;</text></p></li>
<li label="(2)"><p num="n"><text>Appeal dismissed;</text></p></li>
<li label="(3)"><p num="n"><text>The plaintiff shall pay the defendant&rsquo;s costs of and incidental to these proceedings, as agreed or assessed. Such costs shall be paid from contributions levied on all lots other than the defendant&rsquo;s lot.</text></p></li>
<li label="(4)"><p num="n"><text>Otherwise, proceedings dismissed.</text></p></li>
</list>
</caseorder>
<appearinfo><appear>Counsel for the <party>plaintiff</party>: <bar>M Ashhurst SC</bar></appear><appear>Counsel for the <party>defendant</party>: <bar>B Coles QC</bar> and <bar>M Sahade</bar></appear>
<appear>Solicitors for the <party>plaintiff</party>: <sol>Le Page Lawyers</sol></appear>
<appear>Solicitors for the <party>defendant</party>: <sol>Oliveri Lawyers</sol></appear>
</appearinfo>
</judgmentgrp></case></caseml>
